thank you very much for not introducing
me thank you
great pleasure to be here when my
favorite places there's some of my
favorite people I mean you're all my
favorite people is it someone I'm not my
favor you're not here so there are so
many points of contact that I can't keep
more in my head I'm going to go back to
basics a bit and just review active
inference and the free-energy principle
in a way that speaks to a lot of the
questions in particular last few
questions we've just had about how we
can migrate insights about perception
and predictive processing to I think the
deeper question of active inference and
querying our world giving as an agency
answering questions about how do we
choose the sparse data in an optimal way
to build oh I see
that's the one yeah can you hear me now
right what was I saying
I was probably said all the importance
action that's right so we're going to
we're going to go from predictive
processing to active inference and on
route I think touch upon a lot of the
key issues that we've just heard about
from a formal perspective from a maths
from a physicist perspective everything
that I'm going to talk about it's
exactly consistent with what I imagine
from a philosophical perspective you
were saying in your talk it also speaks
very closely to some of the more formal
issues about the neuronal code and what
implications that may have for the sorts
of contents the things that we can
represent and happily I'm also even
going to do dogs and cats and
variational what we encode is as well so
that's all good I should confess that
I've got enough material for about an
hour and a half so what
so why I'm going to ask my chair to do
five minutes before my allotted 30
minutes if you can tell me and then what
I'll do is I'll just literally race
through the slides to show you what you
know I'm serious about this because all
the interesting stuff is at the
beginning but just you know have this
been a more informal workshop what you
would have seen so that we get plenty of
time for discussion so seriously just
I'll just stop when we get to get to
that point so the interesting bit at the
beginning active influence and self
evidencing and I'm using actually
influence deliberately here because I
repeat it's gonna be about how we as a
self go and solicit gana evidence for
our own internal models our generative
models of the world I mean going to call
that active infants we're not going to
use reinforcement learning we're going
to use exactly the same objective
function that the variational
autoencoders use variational free-energy
and we're going to put into it or we're
going to unpack that objective function
in a way that allows us to answer
questions about how do you put prior
preferences in how do you do the
epistemic properly I think underneath
all this though it's all about me
interrogating my world so there's a
sense in which that's the interesting
stuff and in light of that we're going
to talk we've rehearsed briefly don't in
bottles but much of the hard work has
already been done thank you very much
even down to the hidden Markov model so
you can skip through those the stuff
that I won't show that I will skip
through deliberately is really fun
neurobiologists that you know you've got
these ideas in play this formalism this
math how would it materially inform your
experiments what you'd look for with
electric f log Rafi or psycho physics
but we weren't really focusing on that
if I have time I'll just show you what
what I would have shown you in terms of
state of the art in terms of using these
sorts of schemes by simulating reading
so composing deep hierarchical hidden
Markov models
work out where to look next to gather
the rent the best sort of evidence for
what you believe is a current narrative
in play that's generating your sensory
impressions right so very quickly you've
all seen this sort of thing before the
idea being that we're going to predict
in everything on the notion of a
generative model your perception is
basically what is inside your head and
sensations are just in the game of
providing evidence for or against those
beliefs I like this example from I think
this is the 16th century famous oil
painter who would paint these still
lives that when you invert the picture
they transpire to be faces and the point
that I would normally make here now if I
have more time is of course that percept
is inside your head that's all we're
actually starting where you ended with
your pretty faces these ideas you are
more than familiar with some of the key
architects of things like deep learning
also figure in terms of the other sort
of brief history of the brain as a
statistical organ generator of
hypotheses or fantasies nicely
summarized here by Helmholtz and the
notion that objects are always imagined
as being present in the field of vision
as would have to be there in order to
produce the same impression on the
nervous system you've probably rehearsed
many times the psychological gloss on
that in terms of deception as hypothesis
testing that getting into machine
learning via people like Peter Dyer and
Geoffrey Hinton lots of lots of people
boring from Bayes and Bayesian
probability theory and statistical
physics to come up with notions of the
Helmholtz machine which were parallel so
this is the old school I would imagine
before it got overshadowed by deep
learning but very much these ideas have
dealt in parallel and if I understand
your talk properly now the generative
models are coming back again and
starting to address
you know that the new technology or the
old equations with the new technology
are now being turned to focus on some of
the questions that were raised in
machine learning by Geoffrey Hinton in
the sort of late 80s early 90s so this
notion as objects being in the field of
vision others would have to be there to
produce the same impression on the
nervous system very reminiscent of
sensory impressions of shadows on
Plato's cave and our job the brains job
is then just to try and come up with a
good explanation for those sensory
patterns
there's sensory sensory shadows and I'm
using the next slide just to introduce
now the formalism and I you know I don't
apologize for this if you don't like
maths take these things as iconic if you
do like maths I think this is really
useful I think it grounds questions that
we were dancing around with wondrous
presentation so if you have a formal
understanding there's a simplicity that
you can appeal to in in providing
various visit ancestors and the
questions that were being posed to the
presenters earlier on so here the dogs
and cats again the idea here is that
were given this sensory shadow say that
I was support my retina was supplied
with these this data and I have to come
up now with an explanation for what
caused these sensory inputs and I'm
going to frame that coming up with that
process of Bayesian inference model
selection which I haven't heard but I
think it's a very relevant concept in
terms of the unitary aspect of the
contents of consciousness we have to
select the best hypothesis on the basis
of the evidence for that hypothesis
inherent in the data in variational
approximate Bayesian inference
that's a variational free-energy hence a
variational autoencoder
so I just want to unpack what that free
at that variation free energy is and I'm
going to use this notation so Q is a
belief is a probability distribution
over discrete or continuous States and I
use discrete States in
let's talk at a particular time and all
I'm going to do is maximize this free
energy functional it's negative free
energy in physics so what is it well
it's just the evidence for my particular
hypothesis - a term called the
divergence which I can rewrite the
divergence between the true posterior
belief the best beliefs about the labels
or the causes of my observed outcomes or
my data in relation to this belief
structure that I'm trying to optimize
crucially I'm going to rewrite that and
in terms of the difference between
accuracy and complexity and the reason
I'm making a big fuss about this is that
it's useful to concentrate on this this
term I think everybody I will be
comfortable with if you like predictive
coding or predictive processing Casper's
predictive coding this is essentially
just the seller squared prediction error
so this is the prediction error that
we're trying to minimize this I think is
very the more interesting term it's the
complexity is how much we have to move
our beliefs away from the prior in order
to offer an accurate explanation for the
data and it effectively schools the
degrees of freedom the dimensions on a
manifold the number of elements in a
hidden state required to compress all
that good information down so that I can
now generate a fantasy or a prediction
that is as accurate as is possible
so those variational auto-encoders they
have something which is you'll see right
through the history of things like
machine loans to sticks they have a
bottleneck architecture you're forcing
the data through a bottleneck with low
complexity simple low degree degrees of
freedom representation minimum
complexity just to keep you Evan Schmitt
Hooper happy and then expanding it again
to actually reproduce the thing that
you're trying to predict that
complexities a repeat can play a very
important role when we move to the next
level of argument which is how we
actually sample the next bit of data in
order to confirm or
disconfirm our beliefs but just an
illustrative example cats and dogs
so what calls this was this a canine dog
or a wolf or was it a little pussycat or
and a bird and worry and even what do
you want cat you see this before us
sorry
he's gonna go with the dog thank you
well-behaved member of the audience sir
right so we have we have a number of
hypotheses in mind we're going to select
this one as providing the most accurate
explanation for these sensory
impressions that próximas is the
accuracy in this instance now after
about the complexity and that's
basically one can rewrite this in terms
of prediction errors and you can get a
nice predictive coding scheme out of
this
you can also unfold this know let's not
go there to make it to make a variation
or to encoder but let's not go over so
that's the basic idea so we're focusing
in this instance on object up tamai
zhing and we can choose many different
schemes to do that a free energy
functional of the data and our beliefs
about those data so it's all about how
our brains are entertained engaged with
the scent the sensory sampling of the
world and of course it was a cat you're
absolutely right but he did seem that
he'd seen the the slide before so the
point being of course you will never
know what's actually out there your job
is just to come up with the most
plausible hypothesis so this was the
illusion of a dog it wasn't actually a
dog but it's still the Bayes optimal
explanation even though it was
completely wrong right so here's the his
the the the key move then getting from
classification based upon genitive
models by via optimizing a variation
free energy functional to active
inference and self evidencing so there
here is there are two ways that we can
optimize this description of the Leo the
goodness of our inference we can either
change these beliefs encoded by our
brain and a way yet to be determined to
minimize this divergence to make our
beliefs much much more like the
posterior distribution much like what to
make our beliefs consistent with their
observations or we can actually change
the data that are sampled to optimize
the evidence and that's the key thing
the what this one function has in it
everything necessary to prescribe both
the perception and the sampling and the
behavior of me practically what that
boils down to is this changing beliefs
conditioned upon a policy to maximize
this free energy functional of of a
policy and changing sensations to
maximize evidence the only way we can
change this through action is by
changing the outcomes and the
observations and crucially what we're
going to do is posit some beliefs over
policies that are or let me first of all
make a key observation here what we in
order to count for action we now have to
supplement these beliefs about states of
affairs in the world with beliefs about
what I'm going to do and that brings to
the table two of that well yes two
things but effectively the same thing
these are these are the reactive
dispositions that Andy was talking about
these are how would I react how would I
act how would I act and what are my P
dispositions - they're acting so they're
going to be the prior beliefs about how
I would behave in this instance so that
PI that policy is gonna be a sequence of
actions bringing dynamics into into the
game at the same time of course because
I haven't yet acted because I've only
got prior beliefs in fighting in a form
stray beliefs about those about those
policies they have to be counterfactual
so you cannot get away from this if you
want to talk about a perceptual machine
that's in a world there's acting upon
that world too worth of the data upon
which it's making its inferences and
doing it's perception you have to have
reactionary dispositions you have to
have counterfactuals and they have to
have some type richness and some depth
and I think that's absolutely crucial
you can't you know this is something
that the formalism I think brings to the
tables and now you have to talk about
what implications does that have for a
sense of self and a sense of agency that
is implicit in in the action now these
predispositions what should I assume for
my prior beliefs about the way that I'm
going to act well we already know from
there is isn't there and I think it's
because it's not connected
what are you into oh oh I see sorry
didn't right we didn't need to be
connected anyway it's a wireless one
March so when did I go silence then a
long time ago does it matter where were
we you know what was I talking about
counterfactuals yeah we have to have
counterfactuals yes so the the
predilections the predispositions to the
way that I will act and now yes that's
right
so the answer is rather obvious because
you just go back to Helmholtz or Cantore
right through to Geoffrey Hinton if I am
doing my job properly then I am
optimizing my free energy therefore the
only belief that can possibly entertain
is that I will behave to maximise my
expected free energy it's as simple as
that
and that's basically what this this
expression here is saying it's saying
that my beliefs about what I'm going to
do my policies my pedis positions my
actions are a softmax function of the
expected free energy that will accrue
under a particular policy in the future
notice also this one this is why I knew
that I wouldn't finish because there's
lots of lovely details there but I just
wanted to point out in relation to the
argument about lots of models or one big
model yeah so I think you're absolutely
right to say well it's probably all a
question of the structure of the one big
model and if you carve the one big model
in the right sort of way
then they it will look as if there are
lots of little models and that's
absolutely true in terms of say
hierarchical cleaving of the model
there's an all another sort of carving
into lots of little models which is
somebody actually mentioned it in one of
the questions about contacts arising or
conditioning so notice what I've done
here just for simplicity really but it
also may have implications for the
efficiency of the
variational message-passing I'm
conditioning states of the world latent
or hidden states of the world on a
particular all all allowable policies on
all these P dispositions that I might
entertain because I am the sort of thing
that I am so that's and so in a sense
you could say each one of these there's
one of these belief structures that is
associated with every policy that I
could entertain so in that sense there
are lots and lots of little models and
then we're going to do Bayesian model
averaging or Bayesian model selection to
select the the the correct model and I
think that would be your argument in
terms that's why there's only one thing
in mind at any one particular time in
terms of what we're actually doing or
sampling or perceiving actively so yeah
that Buddhism so this this what I'm
going to do now is just focus on this
quantity here and this is where the
dynamics gets in so you were pressed
about how far have people got with
variation altering quarters in terms of
putting hidden Markov models back in in
turn and the question was not very far
at the moment so this is I think the
next step in terms of putting this
variational technology into things like
deep learning it's not easy but you have
to now entertain objective functions
that run into the future and that brings
us to again highlights the notion of
counterfactuals these are
counterfactuals that yet to have
happened what we do is appeal to a
Hamilton's principle of least action and
we sort of take a path integral
perspective on this but very very simply
what we're going to do is consider
beliefs or policies more likely if they
maximize a path integral into the future
over the expected free energy now
remember before the N at the energy was
basically accuracy and complexity when
we take the expectation under
observations that have yet to be secured
these two things take very
different roles but that you can still
see the salaah the homologs in terms of
the instantaneous formulation basically
our complexity becomes an epistemic
value or information gained and the
evidence becomes an extrinsic value in
in the sense that it's scores the degree
to which the expected outcomes will
maximize my prior preferences so this is
how you get desires preferences goals
into the expression they are part of a
generic functional that can be cut in
terms of extrinsic and intrinsic value
or epistemic value or information gained
here so this is this is the pragmatic
part of it now this is that complexity
term where we're now trying to maximize
the divergence because the in the past
outcomes informed beliefs about hidden
states of the world we're in the future
beliefs about states of the world will
determine outcomes so now what we have
is this interesting structure here which
is the epistemic value for those who are
mathematicians this is just basically
the difference between beliefs about
hidden or latent states in the world
with and without observations and those
beliefs can only become more precise
more confident with information so it
scores the degree to which getting those
data those outcomes those observations
will reduce my uncertainty about states
of the world and that's why it's called
a we call it expensive values also
called intrinsic motivation in robotics
value of information in economics it has
a number of different names I just want
to quickly go through the special cases
of this because if you haven't seen this
formalism before it may look a little
bit magical but it's not there will be
special cases which you're at least all
heard of or may actually even recognize
formally if I just go through it let me
just take this intrinsic value or
epistemic value or information gain here
I just reproduced it
and I've written it out as an
expectation of a divergence between a
posterior and a prior now if people are
familiar with visual search from formal
descriptions of visual search and what
parts of the sensorium will will be
salient enough to specify the focus of
the next Koenig eye movement what you'll
find is a literature on salience maps
that are usually cast in terms of this
quantity Bayesian surprised so that
makes all of a sense so what we're
saying is we want to we can now
understand the gathering of those sparse
data that maximize my information gain
or minimize my uncertainty and that is a
deterministic quantity that can be
evaluated in terms of this Bayes and
surprises by people like eighty and
Christoph Kok to describe saccadic
searches of our environment this
expectation is actually just the mutual
information between hidden states of the
world and the Associated consequences or
causes or outcome so it's just a mutual
information between the causes and the
consequences under a particular policy
so that's nice because that fits in very
comfortably with people people like
Horace Barlow's assertion that
everything we do is in the service of
maximizing the mutual information
between what's out there and how we
record it principle of minimum
redundancy or the principle of maximum
efficiency them for max principle by
Ralph olinska and so on and so on
let me put now these prior preferences
back in the game but take out a sort of
uncertainty the sort of uncertainty
which is associated with the fact that I
can only see the world in a partial or a
sparse way let's assume let's make
things simple and assume I can actually
see the latent state of the world so
there are no hidden States my
observations are the states of the world
and vice versa
what happens them well we just have
these two terms but the O's become s's
and now we have a very simple expression
which we want to minimize
hence the minus sign which is the Diver
virgins between what we think will
happen given this particular policy and
what we prefer to happen so the
posterior under a policy over outcomes
and my preferred outcomes summed over
time so this in economics is called a
risk sensitive control in optimal
control theory it's called KL control
because this is a KL kullbackleibler
divergence and it's what people would
use in lieu R instead of reinforcement
learning when they want to put the risk
into or accommodate risk so it's used in
plant control quite a lot thank you
that's well actually I guess it Mike so
this was the important stuff from from
the point of view of release from from
the physicists point of view the rest is
just flour is this entertainment apart
from this bit so I'm now going to take
the last sort of uncertainty out of out
of the game and that's basically the
relative uncertainty about what would
happen if I did that and that brings us
now back to just the prior preferences
as though in economics that would be
expected utility theory and in
psychology it might be things like
reinforcement learning so you've seen
that what I would have shown you is an
intuitive example of this intrinsic
value the resolution uncertainty
you know the epistemic imperatives that
drive that sort of good behavior reviews
a traffic light example the point
basically be you don't need to know the
truth state of the world to know exactly
how much uncertainty you can resolve if
you did that as opposed to this and
choosing one or the other is a unitary
thing you can only do one thing at a
time so I'm surprised you didn't say
that you're probably sitting there not
thinking about feeling well enough to
say this or should I say it anyway that
would be and that would that would that
would have been something nice to talk
about so we've seen this is our hidden
Markov model but crucially we have to
think about the transitions from latent
States h's in martyr slides heir states
here that are conditioned upon stuff we
can control
so these bees now are functions of our
policies the transition matrices are
functions of our policies that's how we
get behavior and action into the game
you can write down the genitive bottle
for these things in a generic way you
can then use off essentially
off-the-shelf variational
message-passing and then we get to one
just considerations about the form of
your encoding the processes underlying
belief updating how we can understand
those in terms of a crude functional
anatomy I'm giving you a little example
of a mazes little rat in a maze is it
initially a very curious rat and goes
around working out where through walls
are and then it gets bored once it's
exhausted all the novelty and
environment and then starts become
pragmatic and then I've shown you
simulations that a neurobiologist would
have appreciated play cell activity
mismatch negativity is using that
simulation and then I would have shown
off by showing how you can compose
hierarchical Markov models to simulate
reading of words by contextualizing them
by putting empirical priors over beliefs
about narratives or sentences and then
showing you some simulations in saccadic
eye movements where in we don't look
every word we just look at those good
words that resolve our uncertainty about
the options in our head that best
explain what we will see in the future
and then I would have taken you through
some of the electro physics well this is
a belief updating from the simulation
emphasizing the separation of temple
timescales in terms of these
counterfactuals at different levels of
deep temporal models and then discuss
some of the empirical evidence for that
in their notions in silico experiments
looking at local and global deviations
and compared those to the to the
electrophysiological data then ira
thanked everybody who has contributed to
this talk in terms of their ideas and I
would have ended up thanking you for
your attention thank you very much
[Applause]